Finding Aid for the Paul Chihara Papers PASC-M.0154
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Chihara papers
1965-2005
UCLA Library Special Collections
Chihara, Paul
PASC-M.0154
3.5 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Music manuscripts, published scores, sound recordings, published reviews, and photographs.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 999642473606533
Biography
American composer, Paul Chihara (b. Seattle, WA, July 9, 1938) studied composition with Robert Palmer at Cornell University (where he received an MA and DMA in English Literature), Nadia Boulanger in Paris, Ernst Pepping in Berlin, and Gunther Schuller at the Berkshire Music Center.
Chihara served as an associate professor of music at UCLA from 1966 through 1976. While at UCLA, he founded and directed the Twice Ensemble, conducted the collegium musicum and was composer in residence for the Los Angeles Chamber Orchestra (1971-1974).
He served as the Andrew Mellon Professor at California Institute of Technology in 1975, and taught at the California Institute of the Arts in 1976. Chihara became the composer in residence for the San Francisco Ballet in 1980. He re-joined the UCLA faculty in 1996, and served as Visiting Professor in 1999.
Chihara has received commissions from many world-renowned performing institutions, including the Boston Symphony Orchestra,the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra, the Cleveland Orchestra, and the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center.
His compositional style reflects his interest in asian music, and utilizes shifts in timbral coloring and limited pitch movement.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of music manuscripts, published scores, sound recordings, programs, published reviews, correspondence and photographs.
Highlights of the collection include annotated scores and notes on performance and composition by the composer.
The collection is arranged alphabetically by work title.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Birds of Sorrow (Symphony No. 2)
Series 2. Clarion
Series 3. Concerto for Guitar and Orchestra
Series 4. Concerto for Saxophone and Orchestra
Series 5. Concerto for String Quartet and Orchestra
Series 6. Fantasy
Series 7. Forest Music for Orchestra
Series 8. Forever Escher
Series 9. The Infernal Machine
Series 10. Lie Lightly Gentle Earth
Series 11. Minidoka
Series 12. Magnificat
Series 13. Mistletoe Bride
Series 14. Nocturne for 24 Solo Voices
Series 15. Oedipus Rag
Series 16. Prince of the City
Series 17. Quartet for Clarinet, Violin, Viola, Violoncello
Series 18. Scéne de Ballet (for six instruments)
Series 19. Shinju = Lover's Suicide
Series 20. Shogun
Series 21. Sinfonia Concertante
Series 22. String Quartet in One Movement
Series 23. Tempest
Series 24. Tree Music for Three Violas and Three Trombones
Series 25. Trio for Violin, Bass Trombone and Harp
Series 26. Miscellaneous Photographs
Series 27. Miscellaneous Programs
- Birds of Sorrow (Symphony No. 2), Series 1.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Birds of Sorrow (Symphony No. 2), 1981; 75 leaves, manuscript (Box 7, Folder 1)
      General note
      Spiral bound manuscript (photocopy).
- Clarion, Series 2.
  Scope and Contents note
  Ballet for Lucinda Childs, commissioned by the Pacific Northwest Ballet.
  - Articles and Reviews, Subseries 1.
    - "A Grand Evening of Dance by PNB", April 3, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Seattle Times article written by Carole Beers regarding "Clarion."
      Photocopy.
    - "Pacific Northwest's Triumphant 'Hero'"", April 9, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Washington Times article written by Andrea Grodsky Huber, regarding "Clarion."
  - Programs, Subseries 2.
    - Arts Line - Pacific Northwest Ballet Edition, vol. III, no. 12, April, 1986; 12 leaves (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Program for the world premiere of "Clarion."
  - Scores, Subseries 3.
    - Clarion, 1985; 75 leaves, manuscript (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Enclosed in folder.
    - Clarion, 1985; 35 leaves, manuscript (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Composer's rehearsal piano score with corrections (photocopy).
- Concerto for Guitar and Orchestra, Series 3.
  Written for Pepe Romero and the Los Angeles Chamber Orchestra.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Concerto for Guitar and Orchestra, 1976; 62 leaves, manuscript (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Concerto for Saxophone and Orchestra, Series 4.
  Commissioned by the Boston Symphony Orchestra for Harvey Pittel.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Concerto for Saxophone and Orchestra, 1980; 53 leaves, manuscript (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Spiral bound manuscript
- Concerto for String Quartet and Orchestra, Series 5.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Concerto for String Quartet and Orchestra, 1980; 68 leaves, score (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Spiral bound score.
    - Concerto for String Quartet and Orchestra, 1980; 134 leaves, score (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Fantasy, Series 6.
  Collection of Duke Ellington songs arranged by Chihara for string quartet.
  - Programs, Subseries 1.
    - The Lydian String Quartet, November 8, 1997; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Program regarding a performance of "Fantasy."
- Forest Music for Orchestra, Series 7.
  Dedicated to Yuji Takahishi. The 7th work in a series of tone pictures dealing with trees. See also: Series 24, "Tree Music for Three Violas, and Three Trombones."
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Forest Music for Orchestra, 1969; 12 leaves, ozalid (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Forever Escher, Series 8.
  Double string quartet for string quartet and saxophone quartet, commissioned by the NEA for the Amhearst Saxophone Quartet and the Cleveland String Quartet.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Forever Escher, 1994; 49 leaves, manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
- The Infernal Machine, Series 9.
  Began as a ballet after Cocteau's play, as a project for the American Ballet Theater in collaboration with Glen Tetly. Re-worked into "Oedipus Rag." See also, series 15, "Oedipus Rag."
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - The Infernal Machine, 1979; 37 leaves, manuscript (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Sketches for the work. Includes composer's explanations.
- Lie Lightly Gentle Earth, Series 10.
  Vocal score.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Lie Lightly Gentle Earth, 1973; S.A.T.B.; 5 leaves, vocal score (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Minidoka, Series 11.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Minidoka, 1995; 14 leaves (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Commissioned by The Esoterics and Tom Baker. Spiral Bound score. Also includes cover sheet of composer's explanation of the origin of the work, as well as a translation of Japanese lyrics.
- Magnificat, Series 12.
  Work for 6 part women's chorus.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Magnificat, 1967; 11 leaves, vocal score (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Mistletoe Bride, Series 13.
  Ballet in one act, commissioned by the San Francisco Ballet.
  - Articles and Reviews, Subseries 1.
    - "The Adaptable Chihara Leaps From Movies To Ballet" (Box 1, Folder 1)
      San Fransico Chronicle article written by Marilyn Tucker, regarding "Mistletoe Bride."
  - Correspondence, Subseries 2.
    - Philip Semark (General Manager, San Francisco Ballet) to Paul Chihara (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Letter of intent for composing, "Mistletoe Bride."
  - Photographs, Subseries 3.
    - Roberta Pfeil, Vane Vest (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of Pfeil and Vest performing in "Mistletoe Bride." Photograph by James Armstrong.
    - Susan Magno, Vane Vest (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of Magno and Vest performing in "Mistletoe Bride." Photograph by Ted Pushinsky.
  - Programs, Subseries 4.
    - San Francisco Ballet Magazine (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Program for the premiere of "Misteltoe Bride."
  - Scores, Subseries 5.
    - Mistletoe Bride, 140 leaves, manuscript (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Manuscript (photostat copy) with composer's corrections.
- Nocturne for 24 Solo Voices, Series 14.
  - Roberta Pfeil, Vane Vest (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    8 x 10, b&w photograph of Pfeil and Vest performing their roles in "Mistletoe Bride." Photograph by James Armstrong.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Nocturne for 24 Solo Voices, [1967]; 3 leaves, vocal score (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Composer/performer edition. Enclosed in yellow cover.
- Oedipus Rag, Series 15.
  Also known as, "Love Songs for Two Monsters."
  - Articles and Reviews, Subseries 1.
    - "This Month on WFMT - The Best of Chicago", March, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Chicago Magazine article regarding the premiere of "Oedipus Rag."
  - Scores, Subseries 2.
    - Oedipus Rag, 1979; 14 leaves, ozalid piano-vocal score (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Prince of the City, Series 16.
  Film score.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Prince of the City, ozalid copy, 215 leaves (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes handwritten cue sheet.
- Quartet for Clarinet, Violin, Viola, Violoncello, Series 17.
  Commissioned by David Shifrin.
  - Programs, Subseries 1.
    - David Shifrin at the Y, April 22, 1986; 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Program for the premiere of "Quartet for clarinet, violin, viola, and cello."
  - Scores, Subseries 2.
    - Quartet for Clarinet, Violin, Viola, and Cello, 1986; 55 leaves, manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Scéne de Ballet (for six instruments), Series 18.
  Composed for the Greitzer Ensemble.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Scéne de Ballet, 1986; 56 leaves, ozalid (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Spiral bound manuscript.
- Shinju = Lover's Suicide, Series 19.
  Ballet commissioned by the San Francisco Ballet.
  - Articles and Reviews, Subseries 1.
    - "Something Special Afoot", March, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      San Fransico Chronicle article written by Heuell Tircuit, regarding the premier of "Shinju."
    - "Two Stunning Premieres From the S.F. Ballet", March 22, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      San Fransico Chronicle article written by Robert Commanday, regarding "Shinju."
  - Photographs, Subseries 2.
    - Gary Wahl (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of Wahl performing his role in "Shinju."
    - San Francisco Ballet (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of dancers performing "Shinju." Photograph by James Armstrong.
    - Tina Santos, Gary Wahl (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of Santos and Wahl performing their roles in "Shinju."
    - Tina Santos, Gary Wahl (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of Santos and Wahl performing their roles in "Shinju." Photograph by Jacquiline Poitier.
    - Tina Santos, Gary Wahl (San Francisco Ballet) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      8 x 10, b&w photograph of Santos and Wahl performing their roles in "Shinju." Photography by Arne Folkedal.
  - Programs, Subseries 3.
    - San Francisco Ballet Magazine (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Program for the world premiere of "Shinju."
  - Scores, Subseries 4.
    - Shinju, 1974; 28 leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Spiral bound manuscript (photocopy), with composer's corrections and markings. Includes 2 leaves of composer's explanations.
  - Sound Recordings, Subseries 5.
    - Shinju (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Tape overlays.
      Cassette duplicate.
- Shogun, Series 20.
  Musical.
  - Articles and Reviews, Subseries 1.
    - "Born To Be Much Better - Shogun Composer Paul Chihara Speaks Out Against The Show", December 31, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Theater Week article written by John Harris.
      Two photocopies.
    - [Advertisement], May 6, 1990
      New York Times full page advertisement for "Shogun."
  - Programs, Subseries 2.
    - Playbill - Marquis Theater, November 15, 1990; 50 leaves
      Program for the opening night of "Shogun."
      Original program, and photocopies of program selections.
  - Scores, Subseries 3.
    - Shogun, [1980]; 280 leaves, piano vocal prints (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Sinfonia Concertante, Series 21.
  Commissioned by the NEA for the Boston Symphony Chamber Players.
  - Programs, Subseries 1.
    - Boston Symphony Chamber Players, January 20, 1980; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Program for the premiere of "Sinfonia Concertante."
  - Scores, Subseries 2.
    - Sinfonia Concertante, 1979; 100 leaves, manuscript (Box 5, Folder 2)
- String Quartet in One Movement, Series 22.
  Dedicated to the Philadelphia String Quartet.
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - String Quartet in One Movement, 1965; 8 leaves, score (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Tempest, Series 23.
  Ballet written for the San Francisco Ballet.
  - Articles and Reviews, Subseries 1.
    - "'Tempest' Takes Ballet Audience By Storm", May 25, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Milwaukee Journal Sentinel article written by Tom Strini, regarding "Tempest."
  - Scores, Subseries 2.
    - The Tempest, 1980; 150 leaves, ozalid (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Spiral bound ozalid.
  - Sound Recordings, Subseries 3.
    - Tempest, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Compact disc.
- Tree Music for Three Violas and Three Trombones, Series 24.
  Work is the first in a series of tone pictures dealing with trees. See also: Series 7, "Forest Music for Orchestra."
  - Scores, Subseries 1.
    - Tree Music for Three Violas and Three Trombones, 1966; 10 leaves, manuscript (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Includes cover sheet attached to a card containing composer's notes.
    - Tree Music for Three Violas and Three Trombones, 1966; 10 leaves, manuscript (Box 5, Folder 2)
      With composer's notes.
- Trio for Violin, Bass Trombone and Harp, Series 25.
  Commissioned by the For The Love of Music Ensemble.
  - Programs, Subseries 1.
    - Merkin Concert Hall, February 16, 1988; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Program for the world premiere of "Trio for violin, bass trombone, and harp."
  - Scores, Subseries 2.
    - Trio for Violin, Bass Trombone and Harp, 1988; 32 leaves, manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Photographs, Series 26.
  - Paul Chihara, Yuji Takahishi, Leon Kirchner, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Photograph taken at the Ojai Music Festival.
- Miscellaneous Programs, Series 27.
  - Carnegie Mellon Music, November 6, 1997; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Program for the lecture, "Composing for the Movies."